<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A brief discovery of that which is called the popish religion with a word to the Inquisition discovering their seat of injustice and cruelty, and also a word to them who are in bondage under this deceit that upholdeth the Beasts worship. And a word to the Pope who calls himself a bishop and is not, his throne of deceit is discovered, by the Spirit of the eternall God. / Given forth by me who am called of the world. A. Gargill.</title>
            <author>Gargill, Anne.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1656</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 83 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 18 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A85807</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing G258</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E887_2</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R202273</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99862618</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99862618</idno>
            <idno type="VID">114783</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A85807)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 114783)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 133:E887[2])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A brief discovery of that which is called the popish religion with a word to the Inquisition discovering their seat of injustice and cruelty, and also a word to them who are in bondage under this deceit that upholdeth the Beasts worship. And a word to the Pope who calls himself a bishop and is not, his throne of deceit is discovered, by the Spirit of the eternall God. / Given forth by me who am called of the world. A. Gargill.</title>
                  <author>Gargill, Anne.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 29, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Giles Calvert at the black spread Eagle neer the west end of Pauls,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London; :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1656.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "7ber 12" [i.e. September 12].</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catholic Church --  Controversial literature --  Quaker authors --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:114783:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A BRIEF DISCOVERY OF THAT Which is called the Popiſh RELIGION WITH A word to the Inquiſition diſcovering their ſeat of Injuſtice and Cruelty,</p>
            <p>And alſo a word to them who are in Bondage under this deceit that upholdeth the Beaſts Worſhip.</p>
            <p>And a word to the Pope who calls himſelf a Biſhop and is not, his throne of deceit is diſcovered, by the Spirit of the Eternall God.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Given forth by me who am called of the World.</hi> A. GARGILL</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Giles Calvert</hi> at the black ſpread Eagle neer the Weſt end of <hi>Pauls,</hi> 1656.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:114783:2"/>
            <head>A brief diſcovery of that which is called the Popiſh Religion, with a word to the Inquiſition, diſcovering their ſeat of Injuſtice and Cruelty, and alſo a word to them who are in Bondage under this deceipt, that upholdeth the Beaſts worſhip.</head>
            <div type="part">
               <opener>
                  <salute>FRIENDS,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Inde the light of Chriſt Jeſus, him, by whom the world was made, who will lead you to righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs, and holineſs, in him there is no ſtrife, nor no debate; you are guided by the Prince of the Air, who leadeth to iniquity, and all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of abhomination againſt the Lord and his anointed; your imitation, and falſe worſhip lyes in the fall of <hi>Adam,</hi> your guide is the Serpent full of ſubtilty, and invention, and pride, cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſneſs, and all manner of evill is exalted in you; your fruits are the deeds or darkneſs out of the right of Jeſus; bring your deeds to the light, let that judge your ways and practiſes, whether they are wrought in God yea or nay. God is the guide of all them that fear him, he leads unto righteouſneſs; but your wayes are deceit, and abhomination, they are wrought by Magick art, the Magicians of <hi>Egypt</hi> imitated <hi>Moſes,</hi> who had the power of God, by the Devill were the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> guided to work by ſubtilty for their glory, but that glory had an end, and ſo will yours in time, the Lords hand is againſt your deceit, your abhominable pride and wickedneſs which ſtandeth in your deceit, you are deceivers of ſouls for your own advantage, you ſeek the fleece and ſtarve the flock, by this your magick authority and conjuration, which you have gathered in by the Prince of the air; the Devill is your God whom you ſerve, he was a deceiver from the beginning, by him you are led to deceive the
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:114783:3"/>people of their eternall happineſs to be led by your conjuration, and your Necromancy, The Prince of the air leadeth you to airy imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations without ſubſtance, Chriſt is the ſubſtance, and him you know not to be your guide, you are guided by another, the Harlot is your guide, the well favoured Harlot decking her ſelf, making of Images, and painting of likeneſſes of things without ſubſtance; the ſubſtance of all you know not, the light of Jeſus is a ſtranger to your wicked minds, who are bent againſt God, and his wayes you deſpiſe, and caſt them be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind your backs; you are the painted whore in this your practiſe. The Devil is your Head, and Chriſt the Head you know not, the Lamb of Innocency you never knew to be the light of the world, who leads to plainneſs, and honeſty, your comfort is in this life, you know no other but that which leads to pride, and all manner of abhomination, cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſneſs is your root, it is the root of evill, by which the Canker en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, it hath corrupted your hearts, and minds, and made you ſubject to the Devil, who is a Maſter, and Lord over you; you are his ſervants whom ye obey; your Idoll Gods in them you live, and have your being, your being is in this life, you know no other, nor no better: Pride is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alted in you, you know not him that leads out of the world, nor out of the things of the world, for your being is in them; your being is in the duſt among the Serpents and beaſts, and ravenous Wolves, and with them you do feed in the wilderneſs of deſtruction: deſtruction is your end, if you do not repent and ſerve the living God, who leadeth out of all babels, and trifels, pleaſing the mind with the fruitleſs works of darkneſs, your pictures, and Images, and your praying to Saints, and worſhipping your dumb Gods, which cannot anſwer, the true God you do not know that leadeth out of the world, he is unchangeable, your God changeth; but our God lives for ever whom we ſerve, he dyeth not, the God of Heaven is our Lord, and Lawgiver, and our Head, and no other do vve ovvn but Chriſt Jeſus the Son of God, he leadeth out of all things that are viſible, he is inviſible to the carnall eye, no man can ſee his face, and live, it is death to the carnall: to knovv God is life eternall, all carnall things muſt dye, and have an end, your Pope is car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall, and vvicked and abhominable before the Lord, and an exalted bubble is he vvhom you call your Head: of that vvhich you call your Church, it is but bables and an invention of the Devill, and by him are you guided to exalt one another, and to make you a God like your
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:114783:3"/>ſelves, Chriſts-Vicar you do call him, where have you learnt that word, or from whence did it come, can ye tell? it is deceit, that is your guide; you plead antiquity, but the antient of daies ſhall judge you all, and all your gathering without God; ſubtilty, and deceit hath upheld your vain titles of Monks, Fryers, and other Orders gathered in by your imaginations: who led you to theſe things? did the Spirit of God, yea, or no; or by tradition of them, whom you call your antient Fathers? Fathers they were of iniquity, Authors of evill like your ſelves; by the Devill are you guided to follow tradition, knowing not the Spirit which leads to life, all your practiſe is in death, it doth not renew your minds, nor change the heart to become holy; for you are deſperately wicked, and murderers, and thieves, and Idolaters, you have ſtoln your Religion as you call it, out of the pit it came, and into the pit it ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn, any one that comes in any other way, but by Chriſt Jeſus are thieves and Robbers, Whoremongers, and Adulterers God will judge, your Harlotting is known to the Lord, who is the Judge of all Judges, your deceit gathered in by the Counſell of the wicked one (who is your foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation) by him you are guided to practiſe that, which neither Apoſtles, nor Prophets did, and yet you ſay your Pope is <hi>Peters</hi> ſucceſſor; where do you read in the Scripture, that <hi>Peter</hi> ſate in a Chair with a triple Crown upon his Head? did not the Apoſtles freely Preach the word of the Lord without money, or any advantage to themſelves; the glory of the world by them was denyed, they feared not their lives to the death, they gave all their ſubſtance to the poor; now learn to know the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, the poor in Spirit ſhall ſee God and live for ever; but you are ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alted above the light, that which diſcovers ſin, the light of Jeſus, who enlightens all men into the world, it ſhews your evill deeds of dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, acted out of the life of Jeſus, your life is death, and death is your end, and that end leadeth to ſelf, to be ſelfly minded, it is death, for ſelf is carnall and devilliſh, did ever you read in the Scriptures your pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe, which you have amongſt you? did ever Apoſtles and Prophets do the ſame, which you do? did they ever ſeek themſelves, or ſelf ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage for the glory of the world, which lyes in death? let the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous in you judge your conſcience, I mean where Chriſt hath placed his witneſs, Chriſt Jeſus hath a witneſs in you all, and that ſhall be your Judge at the latter day: where God is known to be: that is per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, and that delayeth not time, he calleth for repentance by it, which
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:114783:4"/>diſcovers ſin, and lets you know when you have done amiſs, it is Gods witneſs in every one which ſhews them their evill deeds, and when they commit ſin, this judges: now turn to this that it may lead you to life, and peace; but no peace to the wicked, they ſhal dye without mercy; now con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider whether your deeds are done in the Spirit, or in the fleſh; If by the Spirit of God you are guided, then would you not appear in theſe practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, you ſit like Kings and Princes Lording over the juſt by your own invention, and not by Gods direction, or by any example of thoſe that fear the Lord: thoſe that fear the Lord are innocent, and harmleſs like God: there are but two Spirits of God, and of the devill, now mind by which you are guided, and by which Spirit you receive this authoritie, which you practice, doth the Spirit of God lead to murder? let the light judge, or did ever Chriſt Jeſus ſhevv any ſuch example? or did he give you any authoritie to murther men, that be not of your minds? the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſition you call your ſelves, enquiring of that vvhich you need not, buſying your ſelves, and Lording it over other mens conſciences, your own practice you never conſider from whence it came, nor whether it ſhall go; for to the pit muſt all that is exalted be turned; your Idols can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſave you, the day of your viſitation is come; turn unto the Lord all you exalted bubbles, and let the light judge your wayes, vvhether they be vvrought in God yea or nay; did ever Chriſt Jeſus the ſon of the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving God command theſe things, vvhich you do? did ever the Lord of life ſhevv an example to murder? his Spirit leads to ſuffering, through him that maketh vvilling, and not to perſecution, that is your ſeat to deſtroy the innocent, the Lord is preſt under your abhominations, you trample up on the juſt one that diſcovers ſin, ſin is the enemie of your ſouls, and the Lord is a friend to all that fear and keep his commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, this commandement do I leave among you (ſaith Chriſt Jeſus) that ye love one another, and love is the fulfilling of the Law of God, but where is your love to kill your Brother, <hi>Cains</hi> nature dvvells in you, and you are by that Spirit guided, vvhich ſlaies the Juſt, you offer up ſacrifice to the Devill, your ſacrifice, and you are one, and he is one with you that leads you to it; vvhat think you that a dead bable can ſave your ſouls, it you call your Saviour, that you make vvith your hands; you make you a God, and vvhen you have made it you eat it, this cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupts with you; corruptible things are not known to thoſe that live in the Spirit, but in the place vvhere they are to be uſed, and vvhen, and
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:114783:4"/>how by the wiſdome of God, as food for the body, as God in his wiſdome hath ordered them to be uſed, as wine, and ſtrong drink, as <hi>Paul</hi> writ to <hi>Timothie,</hi> as uſefull for the body, and not for the ſoul. The Spirit feedeth on things not ſeen with a Carnal eye, by the Spirit were they gui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to uſe every thing in its place, by this Spirit is Nations redeemed, and Kingdomes brought to nought. Hell is their Portion that knows not that which redeemeth: God redeemeth from ſin, but you dwell in ſin, and are dead; And yet you ſay you eat God. <hi>He that feedeth on me</hi> ſaith Chriſt Jeſus <hi>ſhall live for ever.</hi> My fleſh is meat indeed, and my Blood is drink indeed, but not Carnal as you <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ay, for God is a Spirit, and no fleſh enters that Kingdome, neither can Man by his Spirit know what it is. Man by his wiſdome knows not God, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther can they comprehend his being: for his being is not Carnal, but you are Carnal, Senſuail, and Devilliſh, and the Diveil hath beguiled you, for the deſtruction of your ſouls, to enlarge his Kingdome, his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome is enlarged by the children of diſobedience, diſobedience entred by <hi>Adams</hi> fall when he eat the forbidden fruit, contrary to the mind of God. God is righteous and he leads to righteouſneſs, peace and pure holy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and holyneſs becomes his Houſe for ever: Now where is this Houſe can ye tell, when you make your Idoll Temples a ſhelter for murderers, and thieves. Thieves you are to deceive the people, and lead the blind to their deſtruction: Deſtitute you are of God, when you ſay you will ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice for ſin, and your hands are full of blood, it is not your waſhing with water can ſave you from ſin, it is the blood of Jeſus that cleanſeth, this blood is not Wine to drink in Bouls, as do the Drunkards ſo do you: You cannot worſhip him whom you know not in all your outward imita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. And all your Ceremonies, your Copes, and Surpl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſſes, and Miters, and Crowns, and Croſſes, that are made of wood: and your painted flaggs deceiving the people, and making them follow you up and down Towns and Cities, and call this a proceſſion, it is a proceſſion indeed, for the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill hath poſſeſſed you to make Images like unto himſelf. Images and Likeneſſes is your Religion, as you call it: but he that ſeems to be Religious, let him bridle his tongue, but your tongues are at liberty to ſing, and pray, and imitate: how can he pray or preach that is not ſent; he that is ſent, is born of God, can this birth you witneſs? Chriſt came into the World by the will of his Father and whatſoever he ſee the Father do, that did he alſo. When did you ſee God to receive this authority, your authority is from
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:114783:5"/>your Father the Devill, and his Servants ye are whom ye do obey: Obey the Lord, turn to the Light of Jeſus that leads to a holy Life, and an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent habitation, out of all ſubtlety; You do feed your Colledges with Philoſophy, which is not the Doctrine of Chriſt, but the Doctrine of De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vills. <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaks, <hi>Teach not vain Philoſophy, no Traditions of man; for man in his wiſdome knows not God, neither is he known of God, for God is a Judge of deceit, and his judgements true and juſt.</hi> And the juſt God will be avenged of his enemies, yea, the eternal God will call you to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compt for your Stewardſhip. He hath given to every man a Talent to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove, and the unprofitable Servant ſhall be caſt into the Lake, where ſhall be weeping and wailing and gnaſhing of teeth, out of Hell there is no Redemption. Purgatory (ſay you) is a place of purging and clean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing by fire, the fire of God is a cleanſer, he burneth up the wicked, and bringeth ſinners to repentance; how can you be cleanſed from ſin with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the blood of Jeſus: he is not divided from the Father; <hi>I and my Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther are one</hi> ſaith Chriſt, and he that dwells in God, dwells in Love. where is your Love to one another, you ſell the innocent for money, ye make the righteouſneſs of Chriſt of no effect in your account, when you ſay you can redeeme Souls for money, Money is your portion and your reward; Your plagues ſhall be doubled, yea verily, your plagues ſhall be doubled, for your Life is deceit, and abomination before the Lord; For ever are you condemned if you do not repent, and turn unto the Lord, and his light minde, that you may ſee where you are, and what you do: that all things may be known to be the fruits of darkneſs, which is not wrought in God. God is a worker of wonders, in the hearts of them who dread his preſence, and tremble at his word; his word you know not, neither do you regard it: and yet you ſay you work wonders, where are your wonders? do you know that that leads to righteouſneſs, and holy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and cleanſeth the heart from corruption: your hearts are corrupted in wickedneſs, and yet you ſay you work wonders and miracles. It is a miracle to change from death to life: but where have you changed any. Are not you deſperately wicked? when you tolerate, and allow of mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and make your Steeple-houſes a refuge for murder, and you call it the Sanctuary of God, and ſay that it is a holy place, where is the place that is holy ſaith the Lord? You have builded Temples, and worſhiped Idols: you are Lyers, you worſhip a Den of thieves. You have ſtoln your Prerogative from the Devill the father of lyes, and you are ſubject to him,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:114783:5"/>who is a Prince of darkneſs. Darkneſs hath poſſeſſed your hearts, you have ſtoln a practice from the Devill, and you ſet it up in the ſtead of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocency, for ſubtlety is your order: you have no other thing to preſerve you but ſubtlety and deceit; to deceive the people in telling them you are their Fathers, and that you can forgive ſins. There is but one Father, and one God, and he is from everlaſting to everlaſting World without end, The God of Heaven is a Father indeed, he ſaves his people from ſin, but ſin is your Author, and your finiſher of your end. In ſin you live, and in ſin you dye; Where is your Father whom you ſerve? do you not ſerve your luſts, and your filthy deſires in all things, which your minds run af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter; and flattering your ſelves that you are holy, and calling your ſelves holy men: the holy men of old did ſo as you do, ruling as Kings by your Authority, which you have received from the Devill, whoſe Dominion is ſtrife and debate: and the Spirit of God leads to peace, and to an oneneſs. The Father and the Son are but one, and he that knowes the Father knowes the Son alſoe, with you it is not ſo: you know not one another, but as bruit beaſts in fighting, quarreling one with another, one Nation with another, and one Kingdome with another: this is your fruits of your Religion, as you call it. You have a name to live, but are dead while you live, for your deeds make you manifeſt from whence you came, and what you are, and whether you go, and what you do; your practices are abomination to the Lord, and yet you ſay you have unity and an oneneſs amongſt you, in that which you call your Church, and yet you cannot reconcile your members one to another. For the Church, as you call it, hath ſeven Heads, which you compare to ſeven Hills, and theſe Hills you ſay give light to the Nations; How comes it then that Nations are drunk with wickedneſs, he that is drunke, is drunke in the night, day makes your deeds mannifeſt. Yea, that innocent Lamb diſcovereth your ſubtlery, and your deceit, deceiving the Nations and Kingdomes, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alting your ſelves above all that is called God; Your names are an abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination to thoſe that fear the Lord: Turn to the light of Jeſus, that a new name you may witneſs by renewing of your minds, that light lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth to a new Life, out of the old world which hath poyſoned, and hath deceived many Nations, the World of ſin, which hath been exalted in your hearts. Behold a new Heaven and a new Earth is ſpoken of, but what is this to you, for you know it not, you live in the old World, and yet you ſay you are Church-men; Chriſts Church is pure, even like him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, as clear as Chriſtall is his body, and his members is not devided, you
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:114783:6"/>are divided, you fight, and kill one another, and deſtroy your ſouls through wickedneſs, and injuſtice, Is this Juſtice think you to be a man-ſlayer, and kill them that will not yeild and become ſubject to your abhominations? abhominable is your practice and your deceit; you are grand deceivers this many hundred years, but now is the Lord appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring to lay open your deceit, your nakedneſs ſhall appear even as it is, you can no longer be hidden, for the lightneſs of your Sun diſcovereth deeds of darkneſs: what think you of this, can you forgive ſin, yea, or no? from vvhence did you receive this authoritie, and are ſinners your ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ves, and yet you ſay you have received this authority from the Pope, and the Pope from <hi>Peter</hi> (ſay you) but you are lyars, and the truth is not in you. <hi>Peter</hi> uſurpt no ſuch authoritie, he was ſubject to the Lord and to his Commandements, and his faith vvas grounded upon J<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſus, the Rock of ages, and that faith ſaves from ſin; he that hath faith becomes pure, as God is pure, and he is pure indeed: and yet you ſay you have the Keys of Heaven, and of Hell, and do ſay that this authoritie is left by <hi>Peter;</hi> but you are lyars, and the truth is not in you. A chief Biſhop is your Pope as you call him, Chriſt head on the earth ſay you: hath Chriſt two deads, yea or nay? Is Chriſt divided, what think you? How can this be? Chriſt is the Son of God, he hath no carnall Members, nor no earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Crown, although your Pope hath three, you account him your chief Biſhop: he is a covetous man like your ſelves: in pride you exalt one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother, covetou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>neſs is your Root, it is the Root of all evill, it upholds pride, and pride upholdeth the Devils kingdom; you are proud, and covetous men, ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>fly minded, and ſeek nothing but ſelf in all your pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctices, you care not hovv vvicked the people be, ſo they put into your mouths, and feed your corrupt deſires with filthie lucre; gain to the fleſh is your end; you have no other deſign but to exalt your ſelves, and to be exalted, and live like Kings, it is but uſurpt authoritie; by the Devill are you led, a deceiver from the beginning was he, a ſubtill Serpent, and his ſeed are you who ſeek the fleece and ſtarve the flock, and call your ſerves ſheapheards; Chriſt Jeſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> is the true Shepheard, he giveth his life for his ſheep, he is a redeemer, and ſaveth his people from their ſin. How do you think to be ſaved? By a carnall bit of Bread that you call the Bodie of Chriſt, Impudent blaſphemers, who make an I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doll to your ſelves and eat it, and ſay that it is Chriſts fleſh, and the wine that you drink in Bowls is his Bloud; <hi>he that eateth my fleſh,</hi> ſaith Chriſt, <hi>ſhall live for ever:</hi> and you dye and your God with you, and this is an
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:114783:6"/>end of your dumb Idoll vvhich cannot ſave you. God is a Saviour of his people from ſin; they that feed on that Spirit which leadeth out of car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall things; to be carnall minded is death, to be ſpirituall minded is life and peace, no peace to the wicked, they ſhall dye vvithout mercy, and judgement ſhall fall upon them that forget God. God is judge of all, he is judged of none; nor none can know his judgements but by that Spirit, which is pure; you make your ſelves Judges, and Rulers, by an uſurpt authoritie, you have received from the Devill the Father of lyes, and by a lye are you upheld in your inchantments, and Conjurati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, airy minded men, by that Climate are you guided, airy ſubſtance, Clouds without water, broken Ciſterns that cannot hold water, exal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted <hi>Jezabel,</hi> painting your faces with colours, <hi>Dives</hi> like you be ſitting at your table feeding on dainty diſhes, fitting your ſelves to the ſlaugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter through your abhomination, which is exalted above all, that is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led God, God is preſſed under your abhomination, the righteous groa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth for redemption, but you hear not the Cry of the poor; the poor in Spirit ſhall ſee God, and live for ever, and the rich ſhall be ſent emptie away, avvay with all your vain bables, your im<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ges and likeneſſes of wood, and ſtone, and croſſes. Learn to knovv the Croſs of Chriſt, it will teach you to know God; deſire to know Chriſt crucified in the fleſh, your ſins ſubdued by him that ſuffereth in you, The Lamb of life leads to Innocency out of all inventions of man, out of all carnall things it will you lead, if it you mind, which diſcovers ſin, it will diſſolve your enemies by the brightneſs of his coming, if you deſire to know God, mind his witneſs, it will lead you out of viſible things, and your car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall deſires ſhall be diſſolved. If you mind this witneſs which leads to truth, the lyars mouth ſhall be ſtopt, the iſſue of iniquity ſhall be dryed up, by the brightneſs o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the Sun ſhall the fountains of the earth be dryed up, and the Spring ſhall be ſtopped wherein iniquity doth ab<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>und.</p>
               <p>Abundance of iniquities hath the world gathered into her ſelf, yea the men of the world calleth her mother, through the abundance of her delicates; ſhe hath deceived the Nations and Kingdoms throughout the Earth: the myſterie of iniquitie hath been exalted, exalted bubbles have borne the ſway upon the earth, and the innocent hath been for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten. God hath not been known to them, they have forgot his ways, followed the fruits of darkneſs, and darkneſs hath poſſeſt the heart of man, man hath been led from the light of Jeſus by the grand enemy of his ſoul the Devil, who from the beginning hath miſled man through luſt,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:114783:7"/>and deſire of the fleſh, which cannot ever be ſatisfied from one invention to another, an invention of the Devill is this, which you call your Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, a humane invention mixed with luſt, filth, and deceit, is not this deceit to weary the people with your bables, and your inventions of Beads, Crucifixes, and other inchantments, which your airy minds have gathered in? even plain <hi>Sodomites</hi> do you ſhew your ſelves, ſtudying ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity againſt the Lord, and his anointed, the holy one of <hi>Iſrael</hi> is he called, a name that is unknown by you: he is a good Iſraelite indeed, in him there is no guile, and they that are guided by that Spirit are like unto him kept in innocency, and in that houſe there is no guile, where innocency dwels righteouſneſs doth flouriſh, and plenteous redemption to thoſe that fear the Lord: redeemed are they from the earth that mind the light of Jeſus, by it to be guided, it leadeth from all manner of evill to ſerve the living God of life, light and power, powerfull is he that redeemeth from death to life. This redemption is not of corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tible things, that corrupt, and die of themſelves; he cleanſeth the body and waſheth from dead works to everlaſting life world without end: An end ſhall be put to all your bables and inventions made by the works of your hands; your Crucifixes, ſay you, puts you in mind of Chriſts death, remember he is ſlain in you, in ſpirituall <hi>Sodom,</hi> and <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gypt</hi> are the two witneſſes flain, their Blood ſhall be required of the children of diſobedience, diſobedient are you that forget God; as a bloſſom ſhall you wither, and all your glory which you have received from the Author the Devill. The ground of iniquity is highly exalted among you, who know not God, neither regard ye his wayes, nor bring your deeds to the light, your acting is in the dark, where light is not ſeen, the fruits of darkneſs doth appear, in all your practiſes is not the living God known to be your guide, he leadeth out of all unrighteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs up to know God in that Heavenly City; where God dwels there is no unrighteouſneſs, nor no unclean thing can there enter, as clear as the Sun at Noon Day is the Lord in his glory, his glory exceedeth all fleſh, it ſhall wither before the Lord, and be cut down even as graſs, like ſtubble ſhall the fire of the Lord conſume his enemies, and all that is exalted above the innocent own the Lamb of life, the life of the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous is death to the man of ſin, therefore turn to the Lord, that your wickedneſs may be forgiven, and fear him that cleanſeth the heart, and maketh glad the mind, and reneweth the life, and turneth from darkneſs to light to ſerve the living God, the living praiſe the Lord,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:114783:7"/>yea the living praiſe his name for ever; never can you praiſe God in that nature you ſtand in. Turn to the light of Chriſt, it will lead you to another Kingdom, which you know not, to know God is life eternall, and this life is the light of the world. Every man hath a talent given him, it is the light of Jeſus that diſcovers good from evill, it ſhews you when you do amiſs, it is the check of your conſcience, that tells you, you ſhould not lye, nor ſwear, nor deal fa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſly bring all your deeds to this, it doth not flatter, it is your friend, it leads to eternall happineſs, and that is durable riches, which the world cannot give: the worlds, treaſure is but vanity, and a lye, by a lye are the Kingdoms of the earth upheld in their vain concupiſcence: long, yea long hath the heritage of the Lord laid waſte. I pitty your ſouls that lye in darkneſs, you ſee not the light which doth not change; all is changeable under the Sun, the Son of righteouſneſs never changes; your light changes, and burns out your Lamps, and Candles in your Synagogues of Satan, and you <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ight them again to beautifie, and adorn the place of your luſt, where your life ſtands; what glory is this to the Lord? and what doth it advantage you to do theſe things, God never required? when did God require any of theſe things at your hands? as for going into Cloyſters, or Monaſteries, do you hear any ſuch names in Scripture for Saints to lodge in? their habitation was in the Lord, and not in earthly Houſes; their habitaiton is a Houſe without hands, a building of God; and God is the Author of that practiſe which the Saints follow, no other Author have we but the Lord, he is our Lord and Law giver; you have Lords many, and Laws many, and as you make them, you break them your ſelves; you ſay you ſhould not murder, nor ſteal, nor commit adultery, and you your ſelves are adulterated from God; you have committed fornication with the Scarlet coloured Whore, and drunken the Cup of her Abhomination, is not this murthering of the juſt one, which is a friend to all, and would not the death of any. You have no pitty to your own ſouls, you lye in your Blood, and do not ſee, the God of the world hath blinded the eye, the Eternall eye of God diſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>overs all your abhominations, which are gathered in by your ſubtill minds, and inventions imitating, and pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctizing by tradition; thus hath one generation deceived another. Many Authors have you for your traditions, all from one Root, and the Root is evill. As for <hi>Auguſtins,</hi> Jeſuits, and Caputians, when did the Lord by his Spirit guide you to theſe names? there is but one name to be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by, and that name leadeth out of all names, the Lord giveth a new
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:114783:8"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="11" facs="tcp:114783:8"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="12" facs="tcp:114783:9"/>name, and a white ſtone to his people, and none knows it but they that have it; you change your names from one name to another, but where is the life that leadeth to ſalvation? that you know not; you cannot witneſs a change by the power of God from your evill wayes: and what doth it advantage, for you to change your names? How vain is this? how naked is your conditions before the Lord, you cannot be hidden any longer. Light is come into the world and men love darkneſs rather than light, becauſe their deeds are evill, now will the Lord appear in the children of light to diſcover all your abhominations, and your deeds to be evill. Evill minded men you are, who deny the Lord to be the Author and finiſher of your faith; he that hath faith as a grain of mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtard ſeed removeth mountains, mountains of ſin I mean, which hath been exalted above the Lord and his anointed: you annoint your Prieſts with Oyl to imitate <hi>Aaron,</hi> where is the fruits of this anointing? the anointed of the Lord is pure; purity, and peace becometh his Houſe for ever; where is this Houſe witneſſed by you? Are not your minds corrupted with dumb Idols? And ſelf-inventions, and your Gods is like unto your dead, and dumb Idols is your hearts addicted too; you mind not the living God, that quickneth, and raiſeth from death to life, from the power of Satan to ſerve the living God; your prayers, and inventions is all in the fall, it is <hi>Cains</hi> ſacrifice; all your worſhip is abhomination unto the Lord, you act it in the old nature, which is en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity againſt God, out of the light of Jeſus; do you buſie your minds praying to <hi>Mary,</hi> and making of Images, and likeneſſes, you are not: you worſhip the works of your hands, by vain tradition have you been led, from one generation to another have you lived in Idleneſs and ſloath, not knowing the Croſs of Chriſt that Crucifies ſin; your Croſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of wood and ſtone cannot ſave you, nor redeem you from your vain converſation, you bow to your Croſs and riſe again as wicked, and carnall as ever? the Croſs of Jeſus is not ſo, it teaches to deny ſelf, ſelfly minded men cannot pleaſe God, neither can they in all their imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation performe the minde of God, in that, which ſtandeth in the old nature, all muſt be deſtroyed, all your inventions come down to the light of Jeſus which ſhines in a dark place, dark is the heart of man, a light hath God placed therein, bring your deeds to it; there your fruits may be made manifeſt, whether they are wrought in God yea or nay; did God ever require? or when did you hear his voice? that you ſay you are guided by his Spirit, and you ſay the true Church cannot erre.
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:114783:9"/>This is true the Church of Chriſt cannot erre, who are guided by his eternall Spirit, his Spirit you never knew to guide your minds, and to lead you to theſe practices, as worſhipping Images: you deny the reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection of Jeſus, you ſerve your luſts, and your Popes Invention, by his Articles you are guided to deprive Kings of their authority, and ſit in the ſeat of Juſtice as you call it. If you were ſpirituall there things need not concern you; you are uſurpers in all your practices, you ſay that which you call your Church is above the Law; it is above the Law in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, you neither fear God, nor man; you are Lawleſs livers to make your Churches (as you call them) a preſervation for murd<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rers; he that ſheds mans Blood, by man ſhall his Blood be ſhed. All manner of evill do you uphold for money, murderers, and adulterers, and ſay you can for give them; did you ever read in the Scriptures that ever par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dons were ſold for money? where is your example for theſe things? why do you hide the Scripture from the people? or by what authoritie? were they not given forth by the Spirit of God for generations to come? God excludes none all that will come, may, and drink of the water of life freely, free is that Spirit that leads to righteouſneſs, it ſtraitens none that will believe, and turn to the Lord. <hi>Come all ye that are heavy laden, ſaith the Lord, and I will give you eaſe,</hi> he burdneth none, his yoke is eaſie, and his burden light unto all them, that deſire to live with him; he is a cheriſher of the innocent, and a deſtroyer of deceit, deceit hath gathered into your hearts ſwift deſtruction to your ſouls, if you repent not; repent and turn to the Lord that your evill deeds may be for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>given, come near unto the Lord by the light of Jeſus which ſhines in darkneſs, the heart of man is dark, it comprehendeth not the light; but the light of Jeſus comprehends you all, and diſcovers your deeds to be evill, and all your practices abhomination to the Lord; repent, and turn in ſin, for now is the Lord a going <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o reckon with the ends of the earth; your glory ſhall be laid in the cuſt, duſt is the Serpents food, food for Devils, and not for men; learn to feed on the ſubſtance, which is Chriſt Jeſus, which leadeth out of all, that is viſible up to him by whom the world was made. <hi>In the beginning was the word, and the word was God,</hi> and dwelt among men; man hath turnd his back off the light, he is fallen from innocency, by ſubtilty hath he been led to the deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of his ſoul. The light of Jeſus ſhews you this; that your enemy is ſin, and leadeth to a deſolate habitation, which is not in God. God is a finiſher of faith, and the Author of righteouſneſs, peace and pure
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:114783:10"/>holineſs. The Devil he is the Author of ſin, he was a lyar from the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, and by a lye are you led to diſobey the Lord of life. The living praiſe the Lord, yea, the living praiſe the Lord for ever and ever; never wil God forſake thoſe that fear his preſence, and tremble at his word; tremble all ye Cedars of the earth, for your glory ſhall be ſhaken, by the bright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of his coming, ſhall your glory be conſumed, even as Chaff before the wind ſhall the wicked be ſcattered, and their glory brought to nought; the glory of the earth ſhall be laid waſte, God will leved the Hills, and mountains. The barren mountains ſhall become a fruitfull field, and the true ſhepheard ſhall be known, he will feed his Sheep in the plain where no Wolves ſhall come to devoure them; he is a good Shepheard indeed, he carryeth his Lambs in his arms, he preſerves the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent, and feedeth the Hungry, and the rich he ſends empty away. Away with all your abhominations, that you have gathered into your ſelves in the wrong nature, and fed the fleſh, and ſtarved your ſouls, by the fall is fleſh exalted, and by the Spirit is righteouſneſs increaſed the Spirit of God I mean, which leadeth out of luſt, covetouſneſs, pride, and mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, all this hath been gathered in by the fall of <hi>Adam:</hi> In that nature you are, you cannot witneſs a new life, and yet you ſay you are holy, and unblameable in your actings towards God. God you never knew, your actions is denyed by the Lord of life, for they are but dead works; your works is like your ſelves, fruitleſs trees you are, full of leaves bearing, no fruit at all. The fruits of righteouſneſs is a ſtranger amongſt you, your deceit is known to the Lord, you can no longer be hidden; light i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> come into the world, and men love darkneſs rather than light, becauſe their deeds are evill. The evill root hath been advanced, the Nations have been drunk, all manner of abhominations have been gathered in, and men thereon have built Palaces, and Towers, and ſtrong Holds; Theſe Camps ſhall be broken, the Army of the Lord ſhall deſtroy their buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings; he is a coming with ten thouſands of his Angels to reckon with all fleſh; he will gather his people together out of all corners of the earth, yea, throughout the earth will God be known; his kingdom ſhal be advanced; Long, long, hath the Heritage of the Lord laid waſte; now ſhall the Harlot be diſcovered, the wicked have been exalted, and the poor have ſuff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>red, the Lamb of innocencie hath been forgotten amongſt men; men have gloryed in their ſhame, and gathered to themſelves ſwift deſtruction. Come down unto the Lord and mind innocencie, it it will bring you to know an eternall kingdom, that kingdom is endleſs,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:114783:10"/>that kingdom can no man enter by ſubtilty or deceit; even as a child is nouriſhed by the mother, ſo doth the Lord tender thoſe that feed on him: this food is an innocent life, and an harmleſs habitation, an habitation of glory is the kingdom of God, and none can enter there but thoſe, that are ſanctified; by his blood he redeemeth from ſin, and death; death is the end of all under the Sun. The Son of righteouſneſs maketh his enemies to fly before him, he diſſolveth their glory by the brightneſs of his coming; this appearance is not by mans will, it cuts the rebellious minds in ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and bringeth down the lofty in their imaginations; Is not this an imagination to conſecrate, and make holy (as you ſay) water to ſprinkle your faces, what is it that can make holy? you being ſinners your ſelves, you do call it holy water, where have you this rule; or by what Spirit are you guided, If by the Spirit, of God then would your fruits appear to be like unto him; that Spirit begets like it ſelf, things that are ſanctified, thoſe that are ſanctified, are by that Spirit guided, their fruits are not like yours; ſetting your ſelves in an exalted ſeat of judgement, and you your ſelves are to be judged by that eternall Spirit, which cuts down tranſgreſſion, you your ſelves being found tranſgreſſors, how can you ſit in the ſeat of judgement with a ſafe conſcience to judge o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, and you your ſelves as corrupt as any, and as ſinfull as any, how can you then be ſo impudent, as to take upon you theſe things, which belong to the Lord onely? he is judge of all, he is judged of none, and his judgement is true, and ſhall ſtand eternally for ever and ever; never will God be known in this nature which you act in, as your committing of murther; did ever Chriſt when he was upon the earth murther thoſe, that would not believe in him? have you received this example from the Lord of life? let that in your conſciences judge whether theſe fruits be wrought in God yea or nay, if not of God, then muſt it be of the Devil, he was a murtherer from the beginning, and ſo are you; even as <hi>Cain</hi> ſlew <hi>Abel,</hi> ſo are you murtherers, and manſlayers: your foundation is tyranny; againſt the living God are you bent; your miſchief is made manifeſt to the children of light, and life, they who lives in God ſees the dark world how it ſtands advanced in mans heart, the world is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleated in the children of diſobedience, and they are become Princes by their Author the Devill, he is the Prince of darkneſs, and darkneſs poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſeth their hearts that is guided by lyes; that Spirit ſay you can't erre; which you are guided by; now conſider with your ſelves, what Spirit it is, whether it be the Spirit of God, or of the Devil; did ever God com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand you to murder men yea or nay? minde your ſelves, and in this
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:114783:11"/>practiſe do not you uphold adulterers, murderers, and thieves? If they be never ſo wicked, you let them alone in their ſin, if they will but ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour you, who calls your ſelves the Romiſh Church; you are Romans indeed, and not Iſraelites, your fruits makes you manifeſt what you are, and from whence you came, and whether you will go, if you do not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent, to him which is the Author and the finiſher of all wickedneſs, it is he that gives you glory, this glory which ſhall become deſolate; deſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation is your portion, if you minde not the light of Jeſus to guide your minds, and ſtay you in all your actions, and to bring your deeds to this light, and examine your ſelves, whether they be wrought in God, yea or nay. God is the Author of all that is righteous, he is a righteous God, and judges with equity, and his judgements are true; mind the light in your conſciences, whether or no it doth not judge your evill deeds, and check you in ſecret, this is the witneſs for God, this is the light of Jeſus, which lets you ſee your ſin, wait in it, it will lead you to the Father of life and light, out of all viſible things; it will judge your enemies, it is your friend; turn unto it, God hath not left himſelf without a witneſs; this is his witneſs, that diſcovers the fruits of darkneſs, all deeds of the fleſh are dark, that is not by the light guided. The light is the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to know God; for God is light, in him there is no darkneſs at all; even as clear as Cryſtall is his kingdom, the tranſplendent glory of the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving God is as a Diadem of Gold, as a Scepter of righteouſneſs, to this ſhall all Nations bow, and bend, Kings ſhall bring their glory to the Holy City of the living God; what is your glory to this you uſurpers, and grand tranſgreſſors; the antient of dayes ſhall levell your glory and your ſhame ſhall appear naked as it is; you are naked, you are naked indeed, you want the Lambs ornament; with bloody Garments you have long been covered, that covering ſhall ſtand you inſtead no longer, your abhomination will appear unto all, and then is your covering (which by it you have been exalted) rent in ſunder; by the brightneſs of his coming is your deeds made manifeſt, who act in the fleſh without God in the the world. Are not you aſhamed of your practice to ſit like Princes in a Palace with your ſilver Inkhorns, and your Gold Rings on your fingers, and your ſilken Carpet, and with your Rooms hung, and decked with ornaments, even as a Kings Palace, and antient men wayting upon you, cringing, and bowing, and you but men your ſelves; ye ſeek glory one of another, and ſet the glory of God behind your back, unto you In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſitioners, I do ſpeak. Conſider with your ſelves the author of this
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:114783:11"/>practiſe, whether it be not of the Devill yea or nay. Chriſt Jeſus when he was upon the earth, had not a place to lay his head on, neither did his Diſciples u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>urp any ſeen authority, their habitation was not in this world, but in another, and that world is an encleſs habitation to thoſe that fear the Lord, and keep his Commandements; his Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> pure an undefiled, an undefi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ed life doth the Lord require; conſider with your ſelves all things under the Sun is but vain; turn unto the Lord, and repent of this your abhomination, be all of one minde, and ſet your ſelves to love innocencie, that you may become haters of evill, I mean not ſelf righteous, for no man can ſee God and live; wait on that which is eternall, the light of the Lamb and ſtrength ſhall be given againſt all your enemies which is ſin, and death. The light of the Lamb is not ſo, it leads to purity, peace, and true holineſs, and love. God is love, and love is the fulfilling of the Law; this Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement I leave with you (ſaith Chriſt Jeſus) that ye love one another; he gave his life for the love which he bore to ſinners, and he left his light in the world that men might know good from evill. Every man hath a talent given him, the ſluggard hath a talent, the unprofitable ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant had a talent, and he hid it in the earth. Earthly minded men hides this talent, and keeps it under the abhomination, Chriſt Jeſus was a Lamb ſlain from the b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ginni<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>g <hi>in the beginning was the word, and the word was God,</hi> and dwelt among men; but men loved darkneſs rather th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n light, becauſe their deeds were evill, evill minded men have poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſed t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e kingdoms of the earth, and by the fall lyes in diſobedience, and have exal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ed themſelves above all that is called God, they are ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alted by concupiſcence, and diſobedience, which they have gathered in by the Prince of the Air. Airy minded men have gathered in by that Clymate ſwift deſtructions to their ſouls; from the beginning it was not ſo, when innocencie dwelt in <hi>Adam,</hi> be obeyed God, the Serpent being ſubtle, deprived man of his eternall happineſs, and begot a nature like unto himſelf, and ſelfly minded men are like unto him, their ſeed is d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ceit, full like unto him that ſowed it, the enemy came and ſowed tares among the wheat, and the good ſeed was choaked, and took not ro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t; now conſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>der of theſe things; conſider, there is but two, good, and evill. The good proceedeth from the Lord, that ſeed is innocent, and harmleſs, and would the death of no man, it is the fruit of righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs, peace, it leads unto an holy life, and to do righteouſneſs in the fight of God; and to do unto every man, as you would be done unto; it
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:114783:12"/>leadeth not into <hi>Cains</hi> nature, that ſlew his Brother <hi>Abell;</hi> it doth not teach, to murder men, to be a man-ſlayer; conſider with your ſelves, whether your practice be of God yea or nay; will you deal ſo with any, that you would not have them ſo to deal with you? would you be ſlain for conſcience ſake your ſelves; turn to the Lord, that you may ſee your evill wayes, that by the brightneſs of his coming your enemies may be diſſolved, and that an end may be put to all theſe things, which have been gathered by ſubtlety, and held up by tradition to advance the Devils Kingdom; away with all your vain imaginations, away with all your deceit, away with all your double dealing, all is layd open before the Lord, and he is a judge of it, and his judgement is true, and men are lyers. The Devill was a lyer from the beginning he hath deprived man of his eternall happineſs by a lye; by a lye was <hi>Eve</hi> beguiled, and mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſled with that which leads to deſolation all mankinde; deſplation hath poſſeſt the ſouls of men by the fruit of iniquity, which hath been gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in by his ſubtlety, that is a deceiver. A deceiver is he, who judgeth the wayes of God to be a lye; falſe judgement is ſet up, and inſtead of righteouſneſs, that ſhould take place in mans heart, diſobedience have took place upon the earth; and the righteous Law have been neglected, becauſe man hath obeyed the Devill in the ſtead of God, that is a pure Author, this Author was from the beginning, from everlaſting to ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting world without end; without end is his glory, but you know it not, it is hid from you by the grand-enemy of man, who is exalted a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove all that is called God. God is a beginner of innocencie, and a fountain of life to all thoſe that truſt in him, come all ye ends of the earth, and drink of the water of life freely, he is a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iving fountain, yea he is a living fountain, and all that will come ſhall be tefreſht in that Chriſtall fountain, where the water of life ſprings continually to waſh the Garments of thoſe that are filthie: By his Blood are we all clean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed. O ear the living God of life, and power, for powerfull is he to all them, who truſt upon him for life, and power againſt ſin; by faith are we ſaved; If we truſt in God as a redeemer, Faith is belief, and belief makes perfect all thoſe, that truſt in him for redemption; he that hath faith purifies himſelf, even as God is pure, by the fountain of righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs that comes from God, he is righteouſneſs for ever, and his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom cannot change; no changeable thing can therein enter. The Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly fountain is ſet open for men, therein to waſh, and to be cleanſed to ſerve the living God of life, and power; yea unto him is power given,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:114783:12"/>who is the Son of God, that enlightneth the dark world, and leadeth up to the Father of life, and light. Friends conſider of all theſe things that is herein written, they ſhall ſtand eternally either for your condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, or juſtification. If you believe and repent, God will ſhew mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, if not your judgement ſhall haſten to your Condemnation. The in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent Lamb hath long ſuffered under the abhomination of all fleſh; now will God get himſelf a name above all names, and his power ſhall be known above all powers; his glory ſhall ſtain all fleſh, and that glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſhall be layd in the duſt, who have been exalted above the innocent, and made deſolate widows houſes, and wronged the fatherleſs, and the poor; this hath been the cry many hundred years, the righteous Law of the living God hath been forgotten, and mans will hath been per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed by the children of diſobedience, who have ſtudyed revenge a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the innocent Lamb of light, and life and power; but unto him ſhall power be given to avenge his enemies, a double reward ſhall the wicked receive, their reward ſhall be doubled; the ſame Bread, which they have broken unto others, the ſame ſhall be broken to them; this is the word of the Lord unto you Inquiſitioners, repent, and turn from your evill ways, and come down to the light of Jeſus, and by it be gui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, and it will turn you from dead works to ſerve the living God, that an end may be put to all, that have been gathered, and not by the Lord; from the eternall Spirit, by the power of the living God; this was I or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered to write for the good of your ſouls,</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>
                     <hi>A friend to your ſouls and an enemy to your deceit.</hi> A. GARGILL.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <opener>
                  <salute>FRIENDS,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>TO all you, who calls your ſelves Roman Catholicks. Romans you are indeed, and no Iſraelites, he that is an Iſraelite knoweth the Lord, but your ways are abhomination to the Lord, acted in the deceit of your Hearts, deceitfull is your practice, unſtable is your minds, you are lead by tradition to the deſtruction of your ſouls; your cringing, and bowing it is all in the fall; you bow unto d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ad Images like your ſelves; death ſeeds on death, and that is the end of your practice by tradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:114783:13"/>of your old Fathers, which you call Saints, they are Authors ſay you, and you believe as th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Church believes, and the Church (as you call it) have their Author from the Devill the Father of lyes, he was a lyer from the beginning, and by a lye is his Kingdom upheld in the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of diſobedience; through miſchievous men are the innocent begui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led; beguiled are all they whoſe life is death, whoſe end is deſtruction, learn to live in God that your lives may be holy, and unblameable be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>re the Lord of life, that a living Sacrifice may be offered, and not a dead ſtone; you ſay your Images, and likeneſſes (that are not) is your redeemer; he that redeems is the Lord, you ſet them in the ſtead of God, when you do ſay likeneſſes puts you in mind of Chriſt Jeſus, did you ever Preach any ſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Doctrine? that a dead thing renews the mind? what think you of this? are you not aſhamed to be called Chriſtians? when the very <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>urk walks more unblameable? do you not whore, and ſwear, and murther, and ſteal, and cheat and couzen, and yet you ſay, you are Chriſtians. If you were Chriſtians, then you would be like Chriſt Jeſus, but him you never knew; you have a name to live, and are dead; the living praiſe the Lord, yea, the living p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aiſe the Lord, your moulten Images cannot ſave you, nor all your prayers to <hi>Mary,</hi> and to the Saints <hi>Mary</hi> her ſelf (when ſhe lived upon the earth) claimed no ſuch authority, but was ſubject to the Lord of life, even as was others; who is my Mother, Siſters or Brother, even they which do the will of my Father, ſaith the Lord Chriſt Jeſus; when the Scribes, and Phari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſees came and told him that there was his Mother, and Brethren loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king for him, he ſtretched forth his hand toward his Diſciples, and ſaid, theſe are my Mother, and Brethren, who do the will of my Father? ſhewing that he was no reſpecter of perſons, but loved all who feared the Lord; his love is unchangeable, his love is undefiled; and an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>defiled life doth he require: no other thing doth the Lord require: but ſeparation from ſin, from the beginning hath it ſeparated man from from God; no other thing maketh a ſtranger but diſobedience, God require than holy life, and that you are ſtrangers to: you call your Prieſts Holy men; you have a light from Jeſus, t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſhews you, they are as bad as you, and that you are as bad as them, and where is then your Church? The Church of Chriſt is pure and an hidden thing from the carnall: the Church is hid in God, and none can ſee his glory, but they that are like unto him; his glory is an undefiled life amongſt his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple:
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:114783:13"/>he taketh delight in thoſe that keeps his Commandements, his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement is pure, and holy, and no unclean thing can enter into his kingdom, his kingdom is pure indeed, even of Chriſtail, even as the Sun at noon day, ſo is his glory to them known that keeps his Statutes, and his Law; and this Law is, to be guided by that eternall Spirit, which leadeth up out of the world to the Father of life, and light. This is the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation of the world, that light is come into the world, and men love darkneſs rather than light, becauſe their deeds are evill, be aſhamed of your evill deeds, and turn to the light of Jeſus which diſcovers ſin, the light of God placed in all your conſciences, that tells you, you ſhould not ſwear, nor lye, nor deal falſly; by it God will be known to be a righteous judge. God is a judge of evill, and a lover of righteouſneſs, and he loveth all them that put their truſt in him, Come all ye ends of the earth, and be ſaved, ſaith the Lord, yea come all and drink of the water of life freely, the water of life is the wiſdom of God to guide their minds, and that wiſdom leadeth to an heavenly kingdom, where there is no end; an end ſhall be put unto all under the Sun, when the Son of righteouſneſs doth ariſe with healing under his wings, then ſhall all fleſh be ſaved, he ſaveth his people from their ſin, they who minde this innocent guide which ſhews them ſin, it will lead them to another kingdom out of ſubtlety, and deceit; by ſubtlety was <hi>Eve</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiled. The Serpent was more ſubtle than any beaſt of the field, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed knowledge of good, and evill, ye ſhall be as Gods knowing good, and evill; was not his a lye? to deprive man of his eternall happineſs, leading out of pure obedience, promiſing that which could not be; he that doth evill knows not good, and he that doth good knows not evill. Gods ways is a ſtranger to mans ways, and mans ways is a ſtranger to the Lord in that nature, which ſtands in diſobedience through <hi>Adams</hi> fall. <hi>Adam</hi> diſobeyed God in eating the forbidden fruit, and in that nature hath the Generations of the earth been lead in diſobedience, continually do men act by tradition one of another, and the righteous Law of God is forgotten. The unrighteous p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ant, the ſeed of the evill hath flouriſhed long upon the earth, long hath the Lord ſuffered under your abhominations, now will the Lord call you to an account, you muſt give an account to the Lord for all your evill deeds done in the fleſh; without the Spirit of God you have acted, and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipt you know not what; what hath your worſhips been, hath it brought you to an holy life, yea, or nay? God is holy, and his worſhip is holy,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:114783:14"/>and out of God is nothing accepted; he that dwells in God, dwells in love, and love is the fulfilling of the Law. This Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement I leave among you, ſaith Chriſt Jeſus, that ye love one another; where is all your love, do ye not murther one another: and Cozen one another? and cheat one another? doth not the Pope your Author do theſe things? he which you call your grand Biſhop, and your holy Father you call him; Chriſts Vicar, you ſay, he is; but you are lyers, and the true riches not in you; you are ſtrangers to the Lord, and the Pope whom you call your head, he is your head, you know no other, a wicked man he is, like your ſelves, and a blaſphemer, and a lyer, and uſurper. The hand of the Lord is againſt that ſeat of pride that is upholden by him, his glory ſhall be ſhaken, and that root ſhall be removed, and his end ſhall become deſolate who is a deceiver; a deceiver is he who ſeeks ſelf, his glory is advanced by the children of darkneſs. Search, and try theſe fruits by the light of Jeſus, whether or no they be wrought in God, pride and covetouſneſs, ſelfly mindedneſs; an advanced Bubble is he whom you you call your head. Chriſt is the head of all them who truſt in him, he is a head, and a well ſpring of life; he is a living foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain to them that believe, Belief maketh perfect; through pure obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence is God known to them that put their truſt in him, and ſtay their minds upon the Lord of life; he is life, and light; in him there is no darkneſs at all: all are fallen from God, who acts in the dark, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the light. In the beginning was light, and this light is the life of men, he breathed into <hi>Adam</hi> the breath of life, and he became a li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving ſoul, and this ſoul was perfect untill the tranſgreſſion; this tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion leadeth man out of God, for God is light, and man is darkned by the Prince of darkneſs, who leadeth out of God; now conſider who is your leader, or by whom are your minds guided, are you not buſied in your minds about many things yea or nay? while <hi>Adam</hi> lived in the ſtate of innocencie, he was perfect even as God had him made; there is an eſtate of innocencie which leadeth unto life, and this life is hid in God, the world ſees it not, becauſe of the enmity: the Serpents ſeed, it is the ſeed of ſedition, who hath betrayed man of his eternall happineſs, and his well being. A being hath man in the fall through diſobedience; he lyeth in Blood, even a murtherer from the beginning was <hi>Cain, Cains</hi> nature dwelleth in the children of diſobedience, the nature of man is enmity againſt God; God is a redeemer from that nature, If man
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:114783:14"/>turn unto that which is pure, the light of Jeſus that diſcovers ſin; ſin is an enemy to man, in the beginning it was not ſo; God made man up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right, man ſought out many inventions<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> By the Devill hath he been led to the deſtruction of his ſoul, he is an enemy to all mankinde, and a lyer from the beginning, and by a lye hath his kingdom been upheld; all your invention is of man, a humane invention is your practiſe, of that which you call your Religion, he that ſeems to be Religious, and bridles not his tongue, he is a lyer, and the truth abideth not in him: your to<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>gues are at liberty, who ſwear, and lye, and blaſpheme the name of God, blaſphemy is your practice, your Religion, as you call it, it is blaſphemy againſt God, and the Author is the Devill; and by a lye you uphold your authority; as to ſay, your Pope is a Vicar; what is a Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>car can you tell? or by what authority doth he ſit with a triple Crown upon his head, and a Shepheards Crook in his hand? who is his Author, or where had he this example? did not Chriſt, and his Diſciples wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der up and down, and had no certain abiding upon the earth, they la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourd, and went up and down and preached the glad tydings of the Goſpel to them that would repent and turn from their evill ways; you live as Sodomites, and your Shepheard like unto you, your Pope (it is I mean) ſo called of you, a name deviſed of the Devill, an invention of <hi>Babylon;</hi> was any ſuch name given of old in the times of the Apoſtles, or Prophets? did any man, that feared God, receive authority to ſell pardons for money? Chriſt ſaith, <hi>come all you that are heavy laden, and I will give you <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>aſe;</hi> he is a redeemer out of corruptible things, he is a good Shepheard; he giveth his life for his Sheep; without money and without price may you come<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and drink of the water of life freely; he forbiddeth none, the fountain of living water is ſet open for the Lambs therein to feed; but no Wolves, no ravenous Beaſts, no Popiſh Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lats in that nature wherein they now ſtand; The workers of iniquity are ſhut out of the Counſell of God, their Counſell is abhomination, who are devourers of the Creation; the Creation is given to man to be uſed in the wiſdome of God, but men have abuſed, and wronged that, which was given, and gathered to themſelves ſwift deſtruction: your example, and your Author leads your minds againſt the truth; he that exalteth himſelf ſhall be abaſed. Is not this an exalted Bubble (your Pope I mean) that ſells you pardons for your ſins, and ſay, that they are for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>given, when he himſelf ſinneth worſe than you in ſo doing, even as <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>das</hi> betrayed the innocent for money; turn unto the Lord he is a cleanſer,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:114783:15"/>and a redeemer, his redemption ſtandeth for ever and ever; he that is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemed by the Lord is free from ſin; ſin is death, and death leadeth to the deſtructions of mans ſoul; man is made deſolate by ſin, and death, and death is the end of all them who love their iniquities; love the Lord, he is a friend to all them, who come unto him; come all ye ends of the earth and be ſaved, ſaith the Lord, come all ye people of the earth and turn to the righteous God, he will cleanſe you of all manner of pollution, and your bloody garments ſhall be waſht in the blood of the Lamb, if you re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent; repent, and be baptized that your ſins may be be forgiven. This Baptiſm is not ſprinkling of childrens faces with water, and putting Salt in their mouth, and ſpitting upon their noſes, and under their ears, and croſſing of them with their fingers. Are you not aſhamed of theſe practiſes? did ever the Apoſtles do theſe things? you ſay, you have a Scripture, to put Salt in the childrens mouths, it is ſaid in the Scriptures, let your words be ſeaſoned with Salt; how comes it then that your chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, and you ſwear, and curſe, and take Gods name in vain; this is not ſeaſond nor commendable before the ſight of God, or man; it is unſavo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry before the Lord, to what effect is this Salt? <hi>Johns</hi> Baptiſm it is not ſo, he preached to amendment of life, and to be waſhed, and cleanſed by the blood of Jeſus, who cleanſeth from ſin, and redeemeth from dead works to ſerve the living God, your ſervice is vain, your practice vain, without wiſdom are you guided; the true wiſdom of God you do not know, the Covenant of Grace you are ſtrangers to; you are without where are Dogs, and Wolves, and ravenous Beaſts; in the beaſtly nature, in that, which God cannot own; in the filth, and luſt of your fleſh, you offer up that, which cannot be accepted, <hi>Cains</hi> ſacrifice it is en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity againſt God, you murther the juſt, your ſervice that you do pretend to the Lord, it is abhomination; the juſt God will not be ſo ſerved any longer, for he will be avenged of his enemies, he will call to an account the iniquity of the Heathen; By vain Philoſophy have the innocent been betrayed, that which the Apoſtle ſpeaks againſt; your Schools of lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, which hath upheld the Den of Divills. Vain Philoſophy have ye ſtudied to deceive the people of their eternall happineſs, to advance your ſelves; the Spirit of Chriſt is plainneſs, it cometh not by ſtudy. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocencie leadeth into Chriſts kingdom, even as a little Child muſt you there enter; no policie of man can therein come, it is hidden from that nature, which dwelleth in the Serpents kingdom. A light from Jeſus is come into the world, which diſcovereth all your deceit, and all that abhomination. The mighty day of the Lord is coming, yea, it is coming
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:114783:15"/>upon you all, to conſume, and daſh in pieces, and rend your kingdom in ſunder; the vail ſhall be rent, the dark world ſhall be enlightned by the light of Jeſus, who enlightneth all men; now ſhall he appear in glory, a glorious poſſeſſion ſhall he gather unto himſelf out of the duſt; long hath the heritage of the Lord lain waſte, yea long hath the glory of man been exalted, and the Lamb of innocencie forgotten; howl ye in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants of the earth, yea howl, for bitter lamentation ſhall come upon you, in a day when you know not; know this God is righteous, and his judgements are true, you ſhall give an account for all your abhominations to the living God of life, and power; powerfull is the Lord, he will exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute judgement upon all his enemies, yea, he will be avenged of all his enemies, and bring them under his feet; now is the Lord going to reckon with all fleſh, and the glory of it ſhall be ſtained; his own kingdom ſhall be advanced, the glory of man ſhall be laid in the duſt, and God alone ſhall reign, and the kingdoms of the earth ſhall become the kingdoms of God; for many hundred years hath the righteous Law, of God, been forgotten, he hath been a patient God, and hath ſpared the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then, but now will the Lord call to account your unrighteous dealing, and all your worldly mindedneſs, earth hath been lodged in your hearts, covetouſneſs, and pride, and all manner of abhomination hath been ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alted in your minds; turn to the light of Jeſus that diſcovers ſin, God is a true witneſs placed in your conſciences be guided by that, it leadeth to the kingdom of Jeſus Chriſt, the ſon of the eternall God, this kingdom is righteouſneſs, purity, peace to them which love God, and keep his Commandements; but no peace to the wicked, they ſhall dye without mercy. The wicked ſhall have their portion in the lake, where there ſhall be weeping, and wailing, and gnaſhing of teeth. The Well-ſpring of life ſhall be ſet open to all thoſe that fear the Lord, and obey his voyce; the voyce of God is known to all, but they burden their hearts, and will not hear; they will not bring their deeds to judgement, becauſe they have hardned their hearts againſt the Lord, and his annointed, the holy one of <hi>Iſrael</hi> is he called, he who leadeth from death to life, to ſerve the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving God of life, and power, to him be all power, and glory for ever and ever.</p>
               <p>A Declaration of truth be it unto you, receive it in the honeſty of your minds, receive the truth as it is in Jeſus in honeſty of your Spirits: examine your ſelves whether or no theſe things be not ſo, come
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:114783:16"/>down to the light of Jeſus, and let that judge your fruits, from whence they come, and what they are, and what he is that leads you to theſe pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſes. If by the Spirit of God you are led, then would your works make you manifeſt whoſe children you are; there is that in your conſciences tells you your deeds are evill, and not accepted of the Lord. Turn unto it which lets you ſee the ſight of ſin wait in it in true obedience to the Lord, and power ſhall be given againſt your enemies, and you ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive peace through him, which is a redeemer of his people, his they are that fear the Lord, and dread his preſence, and fear to ſin. This was I moved of the eternall God to write unto you for the good of your ſouls, who call your ſelves Roman Catholicks</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>
                     <hi>Written</hi> per me <hi>from the Spirit of truth, who is called of the world.</hi> A. GARGIL.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>UNto thee that calls thy ſelf Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> thy Biſhoprick is of the Devill, the Devill is the Author, and finiſher of thy authority; where is thy authority gathered? from out of the pit it came, and thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſhall it return. Thy Genealogy and thy authority hath both one root, and that root is the Divel, the Father of lyes; a lyer he was from the beginning, upon that root is thy center, thou art centred upon de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit, thy ſeat is abhomination to the Lord, thy refuge is the Devill, no other doſt thou know. The true God is a ſtranger unto thee, and his Commandement thou never knew; the ſeat of pride is exalted in thee, The Devils habitation is thy fenced City, a City builded upon deceit, is the throne of thy authority. Thy Author is like unto thee, he, who is the Prince of darkneſs, upholdeth thee in thy pride, and thy vain pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe; it is a ſhame to all thy generation to ſee thy vanity, and thy pride. If it they minde that is the light, that ſheweth darkneſs, then will they ſee thee, and whence thou came, and whither thou wilt go, If thou re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent not; be aſhamed of theſe things thou beaſtly man, who taketh upon thee the ſeat of God; was ever man ſo impudent as theſe Generations. In the days of old it was not ſo, the Apoſtles, and Prophets were diligent men, and wandred up and down from one Countrey to another, where ever the Lord did call them. Contrary to their own wits, by the will of him that ſent them, they were guided to do their Fathers work; they preached the Goſpel without gain unto themſelves, or any ſelf advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage; thou ſeeks gain unto thy ſelf, and the glory of the world hath
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:114783:16"/>blinded the eie. Concupiſcence lodgeth in thee, thou art a hater of all good. Good is it for thee if thou repent, and turn from thy evill ways. Come down from thy abhominable throne of wickedneſs and deceit, and caſt thy triple Crown from thy head, and thy deceitfull garments, thy veſtment of Babylon; thy veſture of holy Roodes as thou calls them, are for the fire, the indignation of the Lord will conſume thy glory, thy throne ſhall be laid in the duſt, in duſt hath thy habitation been builded, no foundation but vain imaginations of man. Is not this an imagination to throw thy ſelf in pride, and exalt thy ſelf above all other, he that ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alteth himſelf ſhall be abaſed; and thy baſe practice is diſallowed on by the children of light, and life; life eſtabliſheth the kingdom of God a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the ſons of men, but thy kingdom lyes in death, thou art dead whilſt thou liveſt; thou beareſt a name to live and is dead, thy glory is thy ſhame. Art thou not aſhamed to call thy ſelf a Vicar? Chriſts Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>car thou ſayeſt thou art; what is a Vicar canſt thou tell? out of the pit th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>u haſt ſtoln this title, and by no Scripture-rule; there is no ſuch name there as Vicar, nor no ſuch practice ſpoken of as thou doſt imitate, as to ſit in a Chair, with a triple Crown on thy head, and a Shepheards Crook in thy hand, and the Keys of Heaven, and Hell; ſayeſt thou? Is not this horrible blaſphemy againſt the Lord, and his anointed? can any man enter Gods kingdom by a carnall authority; thou art known to be Carnall, thou cannot be hid any longer, thy deceit is manifeſted to the children of light. Thy dark actings are ſeen by them who dwell in the light of the Lord. Light it is which diſcovers darkneſs. Thou ſayeſt thy Church, as thou call'ſt it, is a figure of <hi>Noahs</hi> Arke, and thou ſayeſt all without thy border ſhall be damned; by what Spirit doſt thou judge? is it the Spirit of God yea, or nay? all other Spirits are for judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, but thy Spirit is ſeen, and thy judgement is a lye, judgement doth belong onely to God, and to no carnall man. Thou ſayeſt thy Church, (as thou callſt it) hath ſeaven heads, and ſtandeth upon ſeaven Hills, and giveth light unto the Nations, but thou tells a lye; ſhall I ſhew thee the ſeaven Heads and ten Horns. The beaſtly nature of man ſtandeth in the four Elements, and in the five ſences compleated by diſobedience, theſe are ten Horns builded upon ſeaven Heads, whereon thy Church (as thou calleſt it) ſtands. The ſeaven Heads is the abhomination of man which gathereth in ſwift deſtruction to his ſoul; the root of theſe ſeven Heads is the Devill, which is the foundation of thy practice, which Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter doth proceed from theſe ſeven Heads, ſhall I ſhew thee theſe ſeaven
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:114783:17"/>Heads, what they are, and whence they come. The Dragon hath caſt forth her poyſon, and infected the five ſences of man, the will and the minde compleateth the ſeaven Heads, where the fountain of iniquity ſprings, which gathereth in ſwift deſtruction unto man; all the ſences are poyſond through diſobedience; even the Smoke of <hi>Sodom</hi> hath in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected, and ſtrangled man, and hindreth man of his well being; A well being had man before deceit entred, through diſobedience was <hi>Adams</hi> fall, and this fall was unto death, and death is the end of thoſe that fear not God; God is the end of all things under the Sun, when the Sun of righteouſneſs doth ariſe with healing under his wings, the firſt nature he diſolveth, he diſſolves all thoſe that lives in <hi>Sodom,</hi> as ſmoak before the wind, ſhall the wicked be conſumed by the breath of the Lord, yea, the breath of his Noſtrils ſhall conſume his enemies, yea, the Lord ſhall conſume their glory, and bring their building under his feet, he will trample on their abhomination: A conſumption ſhall come upon the ends of the earth, and all that is exalted above the Lord ſhall be abaſed, and his own kingdom ſhall be exalted, which ſtandeth in righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs, and true holineſs; with equity will the Lord judge the ends of the earth, with equity the innocent Lamb ſhall be now exalted, over his enemies will he reign, his reign is endleſs, and bleſſed are they who are witneſſes of Chriſts reign. A witneſs he hath in thee who calls thy ſelf a Biſhop, and art none. Read in the Scripture, and conſider the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice of a Biſhop, he is not to be covetous, nor ſelfly minded; A ſelfly minded man art thou, thy fruits makes thee manifeſt; conſider thy ſelf whether or no thy fruits be of God, or of the Devill. Righteouſneſs and peace dwelleth in them, that fear the Lord, the kingdome thou cannot reconcile, thou art an author of iniquity, from thy root doth all iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty ſpring; the Well Spring of life thou never knew, nor thy aunceſtors before thee, which builded upon this root, the root of iniquities thy head, and thy Author, and this head is compleate in thee, thou Son of iniquity; iniquity hath abounded long in theſe Generations, now is the Lord a coming to reckon with all fleſh, the ends of the earth ſhall be ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered, and ſwift deſtruction ſhall come upon all thoſe that are exalted above the Lord, and his anointed, the holy one of <hi>Iſrael</hi> is he called; a name which thou knows not, neither thy anceſtors before thee, nor thy ſucceſſors, the Cardinalls I mean, where have they ſtoln this name but out of the pit, an exalted title, you have no rule for it. Is there any ſuch name in the Scriptures as Cardinals, Jeſuit, Carmalin, Jacobin or
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:114783:17"/>
                  <hi>Auguſtin;</hi> are they not theſe inventions of names, and tytles, which you have gathered out of the pit; as for your Seminaries, and Monks, beaſtly names they are, and Fryers of ſeverall orders (as you call them) which I have not here mentiond; ſhamefull orders, not ordered by the Lord, but by the Devill, which is your Author; he is the Author, and finiſher of this practice. A Company of Drones, who live in Monaſteries, and Cloy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters like drones among Bees, eating up the fruits of others labours, feeding themſelves with the fat, and cloathing themſelves with the Wool, and calling themſelves holy men; is this the fruit of holineſs yea or no? the holy men of old they did not ſo, they did not lye ſtill in a Houſe, they went up and down, and had no certain abiding, they la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boured with their hands, untill the Lord called them by his eternall Spirit from one Country to another, as the Lord did order them in his wiſdom, they followed not the tradition of man, as you do; you ſay, them, which you call your antient Fathers, deviſed your orders, of Prieſts, Monks, and Fryars; the light of Chriſt Jeſus diſcovereth all your folly, and all your abhomination, which you have received by traditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, your Purgatory, and all your ſtuffe, which you talk of; did you e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver read in the Scriptures of a Purgatory to purge ſin yea or nay? is not Chriſt a redeemer, and a cleanſer of them that believe in him? yea verily he is a redeemer to all that do believe in him for ſalvation by no other thing can man be cleanſed but by the blood of Jeſus Chriſt: Jeſus is a redeemer of all that fear, and keep his Commandements; all your ſtaffe which you call your Maſs, and Sacrifice it is abhomination to the Lord, it is a Sacrifice to the Devill and not to God; you Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice the works of your hands; you are hirelings, and greedy dumb Dogs, ſuch as the Prophet <hi>Jeremiah</hi> cryed againſt, if they would not put into their mouths, they prepard war againſt them; you ſay your Maſs is a Sacrifice, and an atonement for the ſins of the people, and you call it the fleſh of Chriſt, and makes an offering of it, Chriſt Jeſus offered up himſelf once for all, he is a free will offering to his Father; but you ſell yours for money, that which you call your Sacrifice, your price of it 8 d. Is not this a ſhame? be aſhamed of all your ungodly deeds, and come down to the light of Jeſus to the witneſs, for God placed in your Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences, that your evill deeds may be diſcovered. I am the light of the world ſaith Chriſt Jeſus, and in me there is no darkneſs at all; this light diſcovereth ſin, and all manner of abhomination; by his ſtripes we are healed, he is afflicted when we tranſgreſs, the innocent Lamb beareth the iniquity of his people; be is afflicted that never ſinned; the ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quities
<pb facs="tcp:114783:18"/>of ſinfull men burdneth the Lord. A rebellious generation hath turnd their backs of the living God; minde that which groweth for redemption, his true witneſs placed in your Conſciences; minde the Cry of the poor, and the Fatherleſs, that the Pi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>grim, and the ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger may have an habitation in thy houſe, thou that is exalt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d ſhall be innocent, and doth not witneſs Chriſts reign; he that is exalted ſhall be abaſed; he that is ſlain in thee is the Lord, thou perſecuteſt afreſh the Lord of life in all thy actings, and thy abhominable practice; ſubtlety have been the Author of it, the Lambs innocencie thou never knew; Philoſophy, and Logick theſe are ſet up, and exalted in the ſtead of innocencie, this can never enter Gods kingdom, it can never enter; the eternall God as bid from all your ſubtlety, and deceit, you are ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers to his ways, yea, you are ſtrangers; that nature (wherein you ſtand) is ſhut out of his heavenly kingdom, yea, it is ſhut out for ever, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver; never will God own you, if there you ſtand, you ſhall never ſee his face in that nature; his face is even as clear as Chriſtall, and his glory excelleth the Sun at noon day. Early in the morning will God ariſe, and blaſt the bloſſoms, which in the night have ſprang. The ſecrets of darkneſs ſhall be diſſolved, and their glory brought to ſhame; the root of iniquity ſhall be removed, and the righteous plants ſhall live for ever. The fruits of ungodlineſs ſhall be blaſted, even as Graſs withereth, ſo ſhall all your glory be burned up with the brightneſs of the Sun. The Son of righteouſneſs will ariſe, and conſume the works of your hands, and burn up your Schools of learning, and and your Libraries of Books, and all your compleated ſubtle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty: againſt the living God of life have you acted confuſion, and builded <hi>Babylon.</hi> This is the whore that ſitteth upon many waters, the floods of iniquity you have ſuckt in, ſwiftly to the deſtruction of your ſouls. Innocencie ſhall guide, innocencie ſhall be exalted above all ſon ever and ever; never will God ſuffer the unrighteous to reign, for the deſtruction of his people any longer. The innocent ſhall judge, and that judgement is true; his righteous kingdom ſhall now be advanced, and the iniquity of man ſhall be abaſed. This was I eternally moved by the Spirit of the eternall God, to rip open your deceit, to all thoſe whoſe minds are honeſt, that they may ſee the abomination of your practice, for ever will God be known in the hearts of them who fear his name, and keep his Commandements: Amen ſo be it.</p>
            </div>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>VVritten</hi> per me <hi>from the Spirit of truth, who is called of the world.</hi> A. GARGIL.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:114783:18"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
